Oleg Shpynov

oleg.shpynov@gmail.com

80999 Waltenbergerstr. 11 Munich, Germany

April 7th, 1986 + 49 177 6904790



Summary

Seasoned research and development engineering leader with strong math background, good communication and teamwork skills. I am leading a group that develops machine learning algorithms, bioinformatics software and scalable computational pipelines for data analysis. Took part in the development of major JetBrains products with focus on the code analysis from lexical analysis to advanced type system development and semantic verifications.

Experience

2016 – today

Research and Development Team Lead

JetBrains Research, Munich, Germany

Head of research and development group. Group is developing novel algorithms and methods for experimental data analysis, building scalable computational pipelines and tools, and working in collaboration with researchers on various bionformatics studies.

- Built a team of software developers with expertise in software development, machine learning, data analysis and bioinformatics
- Lead development of two products: JBR Genome Browser and SPAN Semi-supervised Peak Analyzer
- Developed various open source libraries including Viktor (vector computations for Kotlin), Bioinf-commons (Bioinformatics library in Koltin), big (BigBed/Wig files format support for JVM), npy (Numpy arrays support for JVM)
- Developed web application for scientific papers analysis PubTrends
- Authored scientific papers
- · Onboarding and mentoring software developers of all levels
- Coordinated research and development activities

Applied technologies: Unix, Java, Kotlin, Swing, Python, Jupyter, Pandas, Matplotlib, Docker, Docker Compose, PostgreSQL, Neo4j, Flask, Celery, Nltk, Pytorch, HTML, CSS, Javascript, React, Bootstrap, Git, GitHub, AWS, Continuous Integration TeamCity

Group website: https://research.jetbrains.org/groups/biolabs

Personal GitHub account: https://github.com/olegs

2014 – today | **Students Mentor**

Computer Science Center, Saint-Petersburg, Russia Higher School of Economics, Saint-Petersburg, Russia Bioinformatics Institute, Saint-Petersburg, Russia

Mentored various student project in software development and machine learning including two successful Masters dissertations

2006 – 2013 | Senior Software Developer

JetBrains, Saint-Petersburg, Russia

Main focus was on the analysis of source code in programming languages, starting from lexical analysis to advanced type system development and source code semantic verifications. Developed from scratch the most intelligent IDE for Ruby and Rails - RubyMide IDE, language and frameworks support.

- Developed JetBrains products: flagship tool IntellIJ IDEA, PyCharm
- Created RubyMine IDE for Ruby programming language
- Maintained and developed IdeaVIM plugin (vim emulation plugin, 7+mln downloads)
- Various plugins development including GitHub integration support, web-markup languages editing capabilities like YAML, SCSS, LESS, etc.
- · Participated in conferences on Ruby on Rails as a speaker
- Authored blog blogposts on Rubymine, IntelliJ IDEA, etc.

Applied technologies: Ruby, Rails, Unix, Java, Concurrency, IDE, Swing, Git, GitHub, Continuous Integration TeamCity

Website: https://www.jetbrains.com/

Education

2020	Product management course by Computer Science Center, Saint-Petersburg Product management, startup enterpreneurship
2019	Deep learning nanodegree at Udacity, certificate number: 9GSNRHUA Machine learning, deep learning, models deployment
2015	Microsoft Machine Learning and Intelligence School, Microsoft, Russia Machine learning, artificial intelligence, statistics.
2011 – 2012	Saint-Petersburg Academic University — Nanotechnology Research and Education Centre of the Russian Academy of Sciences, Russia Bioinformatics, molecular biology, statistics.
2003 – 2008	Masters in Computer Science, Diploma with honors, score 4.9 of 5. Saint-Petersburg State University, Russia Faculty of Mathematics and Mechanics, Department of System Programming

Publications

Oleg Shpynov, Kapralov Nikolai; "PubTrends: a scientific literature explorer", BCB '21: Proceedings of the 12th ACM Conference on Bioinformatics, Computational Biology, and Health Informatics, Article No.: 72, Pages 1 DOI 10.1145/3459930.3469501

Oleg Shpynov, Aleksei Dievskii, Roman Chernyatchik, Petr Tsurinov, Maxim N Artyomov; "Semi-supervised peak calling with SPAN and JBR Genome Browser", Bioinformatics, Volume 37, Issue 22, 15 November 2021, Pages 4235–4237 DOI 10.1093/bioinformatics/btab376

Anna Nikiforovskaya, Nikolai Kapralov, Anna Vlasova, **Oleg Shpynov**, Aleksei Shpilman; "Automatic generation of reviews of scientific papers, 2020 19th IEEE International Conference on Machine Learning and Applications (ICMLA) DOI 10.1109/ICMLA51294.2020.00058

Languages

Russian Native
English Fluent
German Elementary

Honors and Awards

ACM ICPC programming contests participant in University Team Winner of Saint-Petersburg State school contests on Mathematics, Physics, Programming

Interests

Machine learning, data analysis, and bioinformatics. Traveling, hiking, snowboarding, diving, cycling, photography.